Register of the Sak'art'velos SSR sakhelmtsipo ušišroebis komiteti [Georgian KGB] records
Hoover Institution Archives
Sak'art'velos SSR sakhelmtsipo ušišroebis komiteti [Georgian KGB] records
1921-1952
2012C55
Hoover Institution Archives
85 digital files
Correspondence, reports, and investigative and judicial files relating to secret police investigative activities and prosecutions in the Georgian S.S.R. Includes lists of persons tried and judicial proceedings in 1937-1938. Digital copies.
Sak'art'velos SSR sakhelmtsipo ušišroebis komiteti.
Soviet Union. Komitet gosudarstvennoĭ bezopasnosti.
Access
The collection is open for research. Users must sign use agreement.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2012.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Šinagan sak'met'a saminstros arkivi, T'bilisi, Georgia.
Historical Note
The Archives department of the Georgian A.S.S.R was established in March 1921 by resolution of the Extraordinary Commission (ChK). The Georgian A.S.S.R. became a union republic in 1936, and at that time the Archives became a part of the People’s Commissariat of State Security (NKGB) of the Georgian S.S.R. Later the NKGB became the Ministry of State Security (MGB), and in 1954 it became the Committee for State Security (KGB) of the Council of Ministers of the Georgian S.S.R.
The responsibilities of the Archives department included receiving and preserving incriminating materials about “enemies of the state” and other “dangerous elements” investigated by the state security institutions. From 1921 to 1991 the Archives accumulated more than 230,000 files stored in the cellar of the 10th department of the Committee of State Security (KGB). During the “Tbilisi War” -- the military coup d’etat of December 21, 1991 to January 6, 1992, against the first democratically elected President of Georgia, Zviad Gamsakhurdia -- the central building of the former KGB caught fire. As a result, 210,000 archival files (80% of the entire collection) were destroyed.
However, many important documents are still held in the Georgian KGB Archives, including those relating to the 1922-1924 guerrilla uprising against Soviet occupation, the 1991-1993 Georgian Civil War (Georgian-Ossetian and Georgian-Abkhazian conflicts and coup d’etat against Gamsakhurdia), the dissident movement, the March 1956 Tbilisi demonstrations against Khrushchev's de-Stalinization policy, and the "Mingrelian Affair" (a series of criminal cases fabricated in 1951-1952 accusing several members of the Communist Party of the Georgian S.S.R. of Mingrelian origin of collaboration with the Western powers).
The records of the Georgian KGB available at the Hoover Archives mostly relate to implementation of the death penalty (banned in 1947) or lesser terms of punishment in the Georgian S.S.R.
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection relates to repressions in the Georgian S.S.R., especially to the 1937-1938 purges and the mass executions that took place during World War II. It contains lists of people executed; legal sentences; directives from the Chief of the NKVD of the Georgian S.S.R. to chiefs of NKVDs of autonomous republics and heads of prisons, military tribunals, and other institutions; memoranda; correspondence; and telegrams. Also included are "execution statements" confirming that death sentences were carried out, along with medical certifications of death. Execution statements were signed by officials present at the execution, including the chief of internal prison, commandant, and military procurator.
Files vary in length, with some exceeding 300 pages.
Secret service--Soviet Union.; Police--Soviet Union.; Police--Georgia (Republic); Political crimes and offenses--Georgia (Republic); Georgia (Republic)--Politics and government--1917-1991.
- Statements regarding implementation of sentences, 1921-1935; 1 digital file: GeoMia_001_r.pdf (Reading room workstation)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes related correspondence and statistical summaries. Arranged by year.
- Alphabetical lists of individuals (809 persons) sentenced to capital punishment or lesser terms of punishment by the Circuit Session of the Military Collegium of the Soviet Union Supreme Court, 1927-1939; 1 digital file: GeoMia_002_r.pdf
  Volume 1.
- Lists of individuals sentenced to capital punishment by court institutions, 1941 January 1 - 1946 January 1; 1 digital file: GeoMia_003_r.pdf
  Includes statistical data, dispatches, correspondence, memoranda relating to abolition of capital punishment, alphabetical list of people executed, and appointments within the Ministry of State Security of the Georgian S.S.R.
- Protocols of the Court in Sessions of the Special Conference (Osoboe Soveshchanie) of the U.S.S.R. NKVD, 1942 August-September; 1 digital file: GeoMia_004_r.pdf
  Includes copies of minutes charging Georgian paratroopers with providing intelligence to the Germans, statements confirming execution of convicts, and memoranda.
- Alphabetical lists of individuals sentenced to various terms of punishment (005 and 006) and capital punishment by the Special Troika (three person commission) of the NKVD of the Georgian S.S.R. with related documents, 1937-1938; 3 digital files: GeoMia_005_r.pdf to GeoMia_007_r.pdf
- Alphabetical lists of individuals sentenced to capital punishment (008) by the Collegium of the Supreme Court of the Soviet Union, or to lesser terms of punishments by the NKVD and USSR Procurator’s Office, with execution dates and related documents, 1937-1938; 2 digital files: GeoMia_008_r.pdf, GeoMia_009_r.pdf
- Records of the NKVD of the Georgian S.S.R. relating to execution of convicts charged in 1941, 1941-1947; 31 digital files: GeoMia_014_r.pdf to GeoMia_044_r.pdf
- Records of the First Special Department of the NKVD of the Abkhzskaia A.S.S.R. relating to execution of convicts, 1939-1941; 3 digital files: GeoMia_045_r.pdf, GeoMia_049_r.pdf, GeoMia_051_r.pdf
  Includes correspondence, orders of the Chief of the NKVD of the Abkhazskaia A.S.S.R., execution statements, and other documents.
- Orders to implement capital punishment and execution statements listing sentences carried out in 1941 and 1942 (to be transferred to archives), 1941-1942; 2 digital files: GeoMia_046_r.pdf, GeoMia_047_r.pdf
  Two volumes.
- Statements on implementation of sentences, 1924-1936, 1938; 2 digital files: GeoMia_048_r.pdf, GeoMia_050_r.pdf
- Court and appeal proceedings from military tribunals transferred to archives, with related correspondence, 1945; 1 digital file: GeoMia_052_r.pdf
  Includes list of court proceedings concerning individuals convicted by military tribunals.
- Correspondence relating to implementation of sentences, execution statements, 1950-1952; 1 digital file: GeoMia_053_r.pdf
- Lists of individuals executed during the August 1924 Menshevik uprising in Georgia, 1925.; 1 digital file: GeoMia_054_r.pdf
- Records relating to convicts sentenced to capital punishment in Batumi, 1937-1941, bulk 1937-1938; 5 digital files: GeoMia_055_r.pdf to GeoMia_059_r.pdf
  Includes execution statements with related documents.
- Records relating to implementation of capital punishment in Sukhumi (Abkhazskaia A.S.S.R), 1937-1938; 15 digital files: GeoMia_060_r.pdf to GeoMia_074_r.pdf
  Includes execution statements and other documents.
- Records relating to implementation of capital punishment in Kutaisi (Georgian S.S.R.), 1937; 2 digital files: GeoMia_075_r.pdf, GeoMia_076_r.pdf
- Records of the NKVD-NKGB of the Georgian S.S.R. relating to implementation of capital punishment in 1937-1940, 11 digital files: GeoMia_077_r.pdf to GeoMia_087_r.pdf
  Includes orders of the Chief of the NKVD of the Georgian S.S.R. to chiefs of NKVD of autonomous oblasts, heads of prisons, and chairs of military tribunals to implement death sentences and create execution statements.
- Lists of files subject to investigation by the Military Collegium of the Supreme Court of the Soviet Union, 1937-1938; 1 digital file: GeoMia_088_r.pdf
- Decisions made by the NKVD and the Procurator of the Soviet Union regarding individuals whose files were submitted to them by the NKVD of the Georgian S.S.R., 1937-1938; 1 digital file: GeoMia_092_r.pdf
  Includes minutes and correspondence.